Guide to the Institute on the Arts and Civic Dialogue Archive MSS.127
Fales Library and Special Collections
Institute on the Arts and Civic Dialogue Archive
1997-2000
Fales Library and Special Collections
MSS.127
16 Linear Feet in 13 boxes
The Institute on the Arts and Civic Dialogue was founded in 1997 by Anna Deavere Smith to support the development of those artworks and projects specifically concerned with social conditions and to foster dialogue between artists, activists, scholars and audiences that could both enhance the artworks and encourage a broader, more open exchange of ideas. The main activity of the Institute was the organization of three summer series where numerous works were created, staged, and discussed with the participation of volunteer audiences, teachers and professors, cultural critics and other guests. The collection consists of administrative records, artist applications, and records and documents of the artworks and theatrical productions.
Provenance
These records were donated to Fales Library and Special Collections by the Institute on the Arts and Civic Dialogue in 2002.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Historical Note
The Institute on the Arts and Civic Dialogue (IACD) was founded in 1997 by actress, playwright, and professor Anna Deavere Smith. Its mission was to support the development of art that illuminates social conditions; to deepen the capacity of artists to communicate with their audiences; and to build an international community in which artists, students, activists, and scholars could work together to develop the artist as a voice in society.
From 1998 to 2000, Smith and The Ford Foundation, the Institute's principal funder, selected Harvard University as the IACD home base for six-week long summer intensives. Hosted by the University's American Repertory Theater and the W.E.B. Du Bois Institute for Afro-American Research, the Institute brought together artists, scholars, activists, and audiences to develop and discuss works of art about the vital social issues of our time. This unique "think-and-do-tank" presented workshop versions of productions, exposing the process of creation and fostering civic discourse on the themes expressed by the work.
Activities included development of new works of art, group discussions, guest speakers, seminars and workshops for participants and selected guests, collaborative research, master classes, public forums and media projects. The Institute's artistic focus included theater, dance, jazz music, song, opera, fine arts, installation and performance art, film and video.
While the Institute still exists today, it's activities have changed since relocating to New York City. As it's website, http://www.artsandcivicdialogue.org, states: "we are now redesigning the Institute with the intention to ignite a new generation of artists who will be able to combine skill, artistic virtuosity and the intellectual passion to pose powerful questions about the state of our world and the ever evolving human condition."
Scope and Content Note
The IACD Archive contains administrative records focused primarily on the practical issues of organizing the summer sessions for the years 1998, 1999, and 2000. Materials include correspondence, administrative hiring records, records for housing, intern applications and activities, budgets for the organization as well as for individual projects, and promotional materials.
The archive is organized into three main series by year. Further, each series is subdivided into appropriate subseries though these vary from year to year. Each year has a substantial main group of administrative records, organized alphabetically by folder title, and a group of artists' applications, organized alphabetically by the artist's last name. Other series present in only one year or another include production overviews, files originating from Anna Deavere Smith or concerning her work, a body of transcripts of meetings and discussion groups. Summary reports of all activities were produced for at least two years. For 1999, the bound report is located in series 2.10; for 2000, the disbound report is located in series 3.3.
For the summer season of 1998, participating artists included Donald Byrd, Dawoud Bey, Shu Lea Cheang, Michael Korie, Keith Antar Mason and Judy Baca. In 1999, invited artists included Ping Chong, Lee Breuer, Demetria Royals, Anita Gonzalez, Robbie McCauley, Bradley McCallum, Abderrahmane Sissako, Art Spiegelman, Merry Conway, Noni Pratt and the Girl's Choir of Harlem. The final year of 2000 featured such artists as Luis Alfaro, Suzzy Roche, Bill Bowers, Ysaye Barnwell, Dread Scott, and others.
Among the records of the many productions produced over those three years are records relating to the development of House Arrest by Anna Deavere Smith. This work was presented as part of the Institute in the summer of 1998; it was staged at the Mark Taper Forum in the spring of 1999 and at the Joseph Papp Public Theater in 2000. Included in this collection are records relating to its development such as transcripts of group discussions, videotapes of its staging at the Institute and finally at the Public Theater.
Series 1: 1997-1998
Subseries 1.1: Administrative Files These files are arranged alphabetically by the IACD folder title as are the folders of the following series.
Subseries 1.2: Artist Overviews
Subseries 1.3: Documentation of "House Arrest" This series is in the order created by the IACD and deals primarily with the staging of the work in 1999 at the Mark Taper Forum in Los Angeles.
Subseries 1.4: Artist Applications Artist applications are arranged thematically by media and then alphabetically.
Subseries 1.5: Discussion materials and Transcripts These materials are in the order created by the IACD.
Series 2: 1999
Subseries 2.1: Administrative Files These files are arranged alphabetically by the IACD folder title
Subseries 2.2: Intern Records Records are in the order created by the IACD and reflect the active internship program of the Institute.
Subseries 2.3: Correspondence and Email Correspondence is arranged thematically while the email is arranged chronologically. The bulk of the email is correspondence sent to and from Anne MacDonald.
Subseries 2.4: Records of Anna Deavere Smith This small group of administrative records are arranged as found.
Subseries 2.5: Artist Overviews This and the next series are arranged alphabetically by artist name and by production name as organized by the IACD. The profiles are generally promotional biographical and descriptive material while the overviews are more administrative and organizational records of the productions.
Subseries 2.6: Artist Profiles
Subseries 2.7: Artist Applications This and the following two series are arranged alphabetically by last name. Only in this year are a large number of scholar applications present.
Subseries 2.8: Scholar Applications
Subseries 2.9: Ancillary Artists
Subseries 2.10: 1999 Summary Report This series consists of a single bound report detailing the activities of the Institute for the year.
Series 3: 2000
Subseries 3.1: Administrative Files These files are organized alphabetically by folder title.
Subseries 3.2: Miscellaneous Project Material This group of records represents a set found physically separated from similar material; it is preserved here in it's original order.
Subseries 3.3: 2000 Overview This is a disbound report separated into folders for each section. The table of contents is located at the front of the series.
Subseries 3.4: Appointment Protocol These files deal with the preparations and logistics of confirming and arranging the year's appointment of artists; they are arranged as found.
Subseries 3.5: Artist Applications-Appointed This and the following three series are arranged alphabetically by artist last name. Subseries 3.8 was found as a distinct group of records though the exact status of the applicants is not known.
Subseries 3.6: Artist Applications-Tentative
Subseries 3.7: Artist Applications-Rejected and Tentative Rejections
Subseries 3.8: Artist Applications-Unknown Status
Series 4: Video Recordings This series comprises recordings of some of the works staged at the Institute over the three years.
Arrangement
Materials have wherever possible been kept in the order created by the IACD. In most cases folders are arranged within series alphabetically by folder title. In other instances folders are arranged thematically by topic within a series but this is less frequent.
Series I: 1997-1998
Series II: 1999
Series III: 2000
Series IV: Video Recordings
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Access copies for some materials are available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Please contact fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Correspondence.; Photographs.; Files.; Transcripts.; Clippings (information artifacts); Theater and State.; Cambridge (Mass.); Administrative records.; Videocassettes.; Notes.; Smith, Anna Deavere. House arrest: a search for American character in and around the White House, past and present; Dance -- Social aspects.; Experimental theater.; Theater and Society.; Bey, Dawoud, 1953-; Barnwell, Yasaye M.; Breuer, Lee; Bowers, Bill; Cheang, Shu Lea; Byrd, Donald, 1949-; Conway, Merry; Chong, Ping; Alfaro, Luis; Baca, Judith Francesca; American Repertory Theatre (Cambridge, Mass.); McCallum, Bradley; Mauzy, Marty; Mason, Keith Antar; Korie, Michael; Institute for the Arts and Civic Dialogue; Harvard University; Gonzalez, Anita; Girls Choir of Harlem; Spiegelman, Art; Smith, Anna Deavere; Sissako, Abderrahmane; Scott, Dread; Royals, Demetria B.; Roche, Suzzy; Pratt, Noni; McCauley, Robbie
- Series 1: 1997-1998, 59265
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains the records for the first season of the Institute's existence. Records begin in 1997 but the bulk of the material is from 1998 and the six-week session of performances, seminars, and discussions of that summer. Materials include internal and external correspondence, staff applications and resumes, artist applications, biographical and promotional materials on the artists and their works, and extensive transcripts of seminars and discussions.
  - Subseries 1.1: Administrative Files, 59334
    Administrative files, arranged alphabetically by folder title, include correspondence, applications, staff information, space and housing rental and other records detailing the logistics of running the institute.
    - Anna Deavere Smith American Express Protocol, undated; 59408 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Administrative Updates on Schedule, Fall/Winter 1998, 59407 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Applications for IACD General Manager, A, 1997; 59406 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Applications for IACD General Manager, B, 1997; 59405 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Applications for IACD General Manager, C-F, 1997; 59404 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Applications for IACD General Manager, G-L, 1997; 59403 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Applications for IACD General Manager, M, 1997; 59402 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Applications for IACD General Manager, P, 1997; 59401 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Applications for IACD General Manager, R-S, 1997; 59400 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Applications for IACD General Manager, T, 1997; 59399 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Applications for IACD General Manager, V-W, 1997; 59398 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - IACD Boston Globe Breakfast-Attendees, June 23, 1998, 59397 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - "Art for Everyone's Sake" Boston Globe Article, 7/6/1998, 59396 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Closing Event: DeCordova Museum and Sculpture Park, undated; 59395 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Closing Event: Tiger Lily Catering, 1998; 59394 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Closing Event, 1998; 59393 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Core Audience, 1998; 59392 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Core Audience Facilitator Payments, undated; 59391 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Core Audience Information Forms (blank), undated; 59390 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Core Audience: Information Requests Sent, July, 1998, 59389 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Core Audience Questionnaires, Response Cards, 1998; 59388 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Core Audience: Anna Deavere Smith's House Arrest, undated; 59387 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Core Audience: Donald Byrd's The Minstrel Show, July 16, 1998, 59386 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Future Core Audiences, undated; 59385 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Correspondence Files, March, April, May, 1998, 59384 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Correspondence: The Brandon Project, undated; 59383 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Chelsea Theater Works Correspondence, undated; 59382 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Correspondence: High Noon, undated; 59381 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Correspondence: House Arrest, undated; 59380 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Correspondence from Mario de Valdes y Cocom: Project Proposals, undated; 59379 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Onsite Performance Network Correspondence Dancing in the Streets, September 15, 1998, 59378 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Correspondence Regarding Collaboration, 1998; 59377 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Correspondence Regarding 1998 Finalists, 59376 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Deputy Director's Files, January, February, March, 1998, 59375 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Deputy Director's Files: Correspondence, Summer 1998, 59374 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Funding Agreement as of 7/10/98, 1998; 59373 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Geography Promotional Material, undated; 59372 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Incoming Email Chronological, July 1998, 59371 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Incoming Email Chronological, August 1998, 59370 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Incoming Email Chronological, September 1998, 59369 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Incoming Email Chronological, October 1998, 59368 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Incoming Email Chronological, November 1998, 59367 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Incoming Email Chronological, December 1998, 59366 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Outgoing Email Chronological #1, 1998; 59365 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Outgoing Email Chronological #2, 1998; 59364 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Outgoing Email Chronological #3, 1998; 59363 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Intern Files, 1998; 59362 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Interviews with Prospective Artists, 1998; 59361 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Kamler, Richard: The Waiting Room, Proposal and Supporting Material, undated; 59360 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Krebs, Joseph: The Street Phantom, Project Description and Promotional Materials, undated; 59359 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Miscellaneous Administration: Huey P. Newton, undated; 59358 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Miscellaneous Administration: Administrative Handbook, undated; 59357 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Administrative Handbook Copy 2, undated; 59356 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Misc. Administration-Advisory Board for the American Repertory Theater, undated; 59355 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Miscellaneous Administration, Copyright Information, undated; 59354 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Miscellaneous Administration: FedEx, undated; 59353 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Miscellaneous Administration--Move to 1430 Mass. Ave, undated; 59352 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Miscellaneous Administration: "Party Line" on IACD Procedures, undated; 59351 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Multi-Cultural Democracy: The Story of Chelsea, MA July, 1998, 59350 (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - Myra Mayman: Meeting Notes, Project Proposals and Correspondence, 2/2798-6/10/98, 1998; 59349 (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - Participant Contacts (A-M), undated; 59348 (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - Participant Contacts (N-Z), undated; 59347 (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - Preliminary Applications, 1998; 59346 (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - Preliminary Planning for IACD, 1998; 59345 (Box 1, Folder 64)
    - Press Release: Event Calendar, 1998; 59344 (Box 1, Folder 65)
    - Press News Clippings, 1998; 59343 (Box 1, Folder 66)
    - Press News Clippings Originals, 1998; 59342 (Box 1, Folder 67)
    - Press Releases, 1998; 59341 (Box 1, Folder 68)
    - Press Requests, 1998; 59340 (Box 1, Folder 69)
    - Rejection Letters, 1998; 59339 (Box 1, Folder 70)
    - Tania Leon, Promotional Materials, undated; 59338 (Box 1, Folder 71)
    - Response Calls and Emails to Invitation to Attend Performances as "Control" Group, undated; 59337 (Box 1, Folder 72)
    - Thank You Letters, 1998; 59336 (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - Thank You Letters to 1998 Participants, 59335 (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Subseries 1.2: Artist Overviews, 59323
    Artist Overview files contain biographical information on artists, performers and theater groups and information on the works presented. This includes material originating from the artists as well as created by the Institute. The series is arranged more or less alphabetically
    - Dawoud Bey, Photographer and Writer: Artist's Profile, undated; 59333 (Box 2, Folder 75)
    - Shu Lea Cheang: Brandon. Proposal for WWW Project Installation; Correspondence with Andrea L. Taylor, undated; 59332 (Box 2, Folder 76)
    - Michael Korie: High Noon: A New Opera/Music-Theater Work Publicity, undated; 59331 (Box 2, Folder 77)
    - Sandy Solomon: Pears, Lake, Sun Promotional Material, Offer to Participate in IACD, undated; 59330 (Box 2, Folder 78)
    - Pepon Osorio, Request for Financial Support of Los Twines, April 1998, Background Material and Budget, 59329 (Box 2, Folder 79)
    - Keith Antar Mason, The Hittite Empire, undated; 59328 (Box 2, Folder 80)
    - Judy Baca, La Memoria..., undated; 59327 (Box 2, Folder 81)
    - This folder was omitted from the numbering sequence and does not exist., 59326 (Box 2, Folder 82)
    - Donald Byrd, "The Minstrel Show: Form, History, Significance", undated; 59325 (Box 2, Folder 83)
    - Donald Byrd, The Minstrel Show, undated; 59324 (Box 2, Folder 84)
  - Subseries 1.3: Documentation of House Arrest, 59314
    Files relating to the work by Anna Deavere Smith. Presented in workshop at the institute in 1998, these files relate mainly to it's staging at the Mark Taper Forum in Los Angeles in the spring of 1999. The materials were apparently once the contents of a single ring binder.
    A video recording of the Institute's presentation of House Arrest is located in Series 4. Also located there is a recording of the 2000 production of the work at the Public Theater in New York City.
    - Documentation of House Arrest: An Interrogation Section I: Preliminary Planning Strategy, undated; 59322 (Box 2, Folder 85)
    - Documentation of House Arrest: An Interrogation Section II, undated; 59321 (Box 2, Folder 86)
    - Documentation of House Arrest: An Interrogation Section III, undated; 59320 (Box 2, Folder 87)
    - Documentation of House Arrest: An Interrogation Section IV, undated; 59319 (Box 2, Folder 88)
    - Documentation of House Arrest: An Interrogation Section V, undated; 59318 (Box 2, Folder 89)
    - Documentation of House Arrest: An Interrogation Section VI, undated; 59317 (Box 2, Folder 90)
    - Documentation of House Arrest: An Interrogation Section VII, undated; 59316 (Box 2, Folder 91)
    - Documentation of House Arrest: An Interrogation Section VIII, undated; 59315 (Box 2, Folder 92)
  - Subseries 1.4: Artist Applications, 59293
    Applications from artists for the 1998 IACD session. Most applications were submitted by fax and are only a few pages long though the occasional application has additional material, photographs, slides, or recordings. The files are arranged by medium (dance, theater, music, etc.) and then alphabetically by applicant
    - Chay Yew, undated; 59313 (Box 2, Folder 93)
    - Application Correspondence, undated; 59312 (Box 2, Folder 94)
    - Leslie Neal Dance: Belladonna, 1998; 59311 (Box 2, Folder 95)
    - Rebecca Stenn: ThePerksDanceMusicTheater, 1998; 59310 (Box 2, Folder 96)
    - 1998 Artist Applications, 59309 (Box 2, Folder 97)
    - 127.0001; Floristas (Talking Back II), by Ruben Gonzalez, submitted as part of application, 1995; 59308 (Box 2, Folder 97a)
      Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
      Video recording, VHS, 3M T30 (on slipcase) T60 (on cassette), RT: 18 min, English subtitles.
    - 1998 Artist Applications--Multi-Media, 59307 (Box 2, Folder 98)
    - 1998 Artist Applications--Music, 59306 (Box 2, Folder 99)
    - 1998 Artists Application--Theater, A-Ch, 59305 (Box 2, Folder 100)
    - 1998 Artist Applications--Theater, Ci-G, 59304 (Box 2, Folder 101)
    - 1998 Artist Application--Theater, Arthur Strimling, Encounters at the Border, 59303 (Box 2, Folder 102)
    - 1998 Artist Applications--Theater, J-Mac, 59302 (Box 2, Folder 103)
    - 1998 Artist Applications--Theater, Mar-P, 59301 (Box 2, Folder 104)
    - 1998 Artist Applications--Theater, R-S, 59300 (Box 2, Folder 105)
    - 1998 Artist Applications--Theater, T-W, 59299 (Box 2, Folder 106)
    - 1998 Artist Applications--Visual Arts, Max Belcher, 59298 (Box 2, Folder 107)
      General note
      Includes 10 slides
    - 1998 Artist Applications--Visual Arts, D-J, 59297 (Box 2, Folder 108)
    - 1998 Artist Applications--Visual Arts, L-W, 59296 (Box 2, Folder 109)
      Includes 1 CD-Rom of work by Margot Lovejoy
      CD-ROM, Requires Windows 95 or NT, 6MB of free RAM, 4x CD-Rom or greater. Margot Lovejoy, 10/12/97-1/4/98, Neuberger Museum of Art, Puchase College, State University of New York.
    - 1998 Artist Applications--Visual Arts, Marlene Phipps, Slides and Promotional Material related to Application, 59295 (Box 2, Folder 110)
      Includes 20 slides
    - Mandelbaum, Aubrey, "Sketching a Common Ground" Essay on Sculpture in Chicago, 1996; 59294 (Box 2, Folder 111)
  - Subseries 1.5: Discussion Materials and Transcripts, 59266
    This series consists almost wholly of transcripts of presentations and discussions of works from the 1998 summer session. Some additional reference materials and transcripts of staff meetings are also present. Files are arranged alphabetically folder title, whether that is artist, title of work, or other topic.
    The audio tapes from which these transcripts were drawn are not present in the collection.
    - Decency Clause Panel Discussion, July 23, 1998, 59292 (Box 2, Folder 112)
    - High Noon: Excerpts from Three Operas, undated; 59291 (Box 2, Folder 113)
    - High Noon Panelist Reference Material for Town Meeting, undated; 59290 (Box 2, Folder 114)
    - High Noon Promotional Materials, undated; 59289 (Box 2, Folder 115)
    - Transcripts: Audio Tape List, 1998; 59288 (Box 2, Folder 116)
    - Transcripts: Brandon Project Presentation, 7/8/98, 1998; 59287 (Box 2, Folder 117)
    - Transcripts: Brandon Discussion 8/7/98, 1998; 59286 (Box 2, Folder 118)
    - Transcripts: Donald Byrd Presentation, 7/9/98, 1998; 59285 (Box 2, Folder 119)
    - Don Byrd, 8/13/1998, 59284 (Box 2, Folder 120)
    - Transcripts: Breakfast with the Interns, 8/11/98, 1998; 59283 (Box 2, Folder 121)
    - Transcripts: Byrd Scholars Meeting, 7/13/98, 1998; 59282 (Box 2, Folder 122)
    - Transcripts: Byrd Follow-up, 7/17/98, 1998; 59281 (Box 2, Folder 123)
    - Transcripts: Dwight Conquergood, 8/11/98, 1998; 59280 (Box 2, Folder 124)
    - Transcripts: Event Coordinator Meeting, 7/9/98, 1998; 59279 (Box 2, Folder 125)
    - Transcripts: Event Coordinator Meeting, 8/20/98, 1998; 59278 (Box 2, Folder 126)
    - Transcripts: First Intern Discussion, 7/6/98, 1998; 59277 (Box 2, Folder 127)
    - Transcripts: House Arrest Discussion, 8/7/98, 1998; 59276 (Box 2, Folder 128)
    - Transcripts: House Arrest Discussion, 8/7/98, 1998; 59275 (Box 2, Folder 129)
    - Transcripts: House Arrest Discussion, 8/7/98, 1998; 59274 (Box 2, Folder 130)
    - Transcripts: House Arrest Discussion, 8/7/98, 1998; 59273 (Box 2, Folder 131)
    - Transcripts: House Arrest Discussion, 8/7/98, 1998; 59272 (Box 2, Folder 132)
    - Transcripts: Howard Gardener, 7/20/98, 1998; 59271 (Box 2, Folder 133)